Welcome to our first ever AMR overtures
discussion. My name is Joel St. Clair
and I am a pastor in Silver Spring and
uh an executive board member of the
Alliance for Mission and Renewal. Uh we
are a group who cares deeply uh for the
PCA and we want to work for a unified,
faithful and flourishing PCA. And one of
the ways we believe we can foster that
unified and faithful PCA is to engage
the ongoing work of the church
especially at places like general
assembly. Now uh the the primary way
that change happens uh to the book of
church order um or to guide collective
PCA churches is through overtures. Uh
you'll hear that a lot in the
conversation that follows that word
overture. An overture, just so you know,
is an ask for action or change that most
commonly comes from one of our 87
prespitaries and ascent to a general
assembly. Uh in the time that follows,
we're going to discuss uh some of the
overtures that have been submitted to
the 52nd general assembly uh in
Chattanooga that will be happening in a
few weeks. uh we will I hope cover some
of the key points of some of those
overtures including a discussion on the
consequences whether good or bad uh of
the proposed changes um what those asks
for action are. Uh today uh we have with
us uh three uh participants uh Dr. David
Coffin who planted and has pastored at
uh New Hope Presbyterian Church for 34
years in Fairfax, Virginia. He's been
married for over 50 years to his wife
Jennifer and they have three adult
children. Uh he uh has uh varied uh
connections through his time in the PCA
at places like Lebri where he studied
with Dr. Francis Schaefer and Oskinis
through uh studying at Ligonier with Dr.
RC Sproul and then doing PhD work with
Dr. John Gersner. David uh thank you so
much for joining us.
Uh Fred Greco serves as the senior
pastor of Christ Church in Katy, which
Texas, which is just uh west of Houston.
He grew up in the Buffalo area where he
met his wife Deb. He'll tell you that
while he doesn't head back to Buffalo
often, the food makes the trip
worthwhile. Uh Fred served as uh the
moderator of the 50th General Assembly
in Memphis and uh has put in work in
recent years to help develop a reformed
seminary in Asia. Brad, it's great to
have you with us.
How Dano uh has been a pilot for 40
years. Uh first in the Air Force and
then for American Airlines before
retiring. Uh he has been married to
Debbie for 40 years. He has uh three
daughters and two sons and many
grandkids. Uh the account apparently
continues to grow. Uh Howie served as
moderator of the 47th uh general
assembly in Dallas. Howie, wonderful to
have you. Thanks for joining. Sure.
Uh all three of these men know one
another through their work on the
standing judicial committee and through
attending multiple general assemblies
over the decades. Uh below, just so all
of you who are viewing know, we'll link
to all of the overtures as well as to
their detailed guides where they have
put in their own reflections and may
fill out some of the conversation. We
think that'll be helpful to you uh as
you prepare for general assembly. Okay.
Uh thanks again to each of you for
joining us. Uh in our first discussion,
what I hope to do is focus on worship uh
the overtures that propose changes uh
regarding corporate worship in uh local
churches. Um maybe starting with the
question of do we need a constitutional
directory of worship? Uh overture number
five. Uh in at least in each of your
guides, you seem to agree that at least
our current directory of worship should
not just immediately be made
constitutional. Now David, did do I have
that correct? That that at least in its
current construction where overture 5
would propose taking a portion uh the
selected chapters and making that
constitutional. You think no. And and
the other uh con participants they they
agree with you.
That's correct.
I I I will say that uh just briefly for
some background in uh uh the 16th
general assembly, we had a proposal to
adopt a the directory for worship and um
it was uh uh chaos. Uh there were uh all
kinds of motions. Uh we had one person
uh ask for a constitutional inquiry on
eight parts of the proposed directory
because it was inconsistent with the
regulative principle and citing chapters
of the Westminster confession of faith.
And finally after hours and uh some
tears uh the assembly adopted uh a
recommendation that we leave the
directory for worship in its present
status in the church and dismiss the
entire matter. Um the I think it would
be impossible to adopt it as it stands
right now. I will say also that Delm
Marva Presbyterian in those days uh of
which I was a member um sent up an
overture suggesting if we do it at all,
we ought to do it three chapters at a
time as long as it takes so that we
could have detailed discussion and
amendment and so on. And uh but I
certainly would never be in favor of
trying to just adopt the whole thing as
it is.
Yeah.
How would you uh you suggested just a
straight no on this. Would you add
anything to that?
Well, one of the things I would add is
um I came into the PCA in 1982
looking through the yellow pages, ended
up going to Faith Press in Tacoma
and fell in love with reformed worship
before I fell in love with reformed
theology.
Black robe, kneelers, red trinity
himnel. Might have been blue at the
time. I don't remember. probably was
blue at the time. Um,
so my opposition to a constitutionalized
director of worship has nothing to do
with my view, high view or low view of
worship.
Um, yeah.
Yeah. One of the questions that I have
asked some people that have written in
favor of it is
for me to be comfortable going too far
down the road. I kind of need to know
what is it that you want to
constitutionalize.
You know, what are the shalls and the
shall nots? Because if there aren't any
of those, then
I don't really have as much concern.
But, you know, if there are some, and
I'm assuming there are some, it would it
would help me my level of comfort to
know what those are. So,
yep. Thanks so much, Howie. Just for
those who are uh tuning in, um yellow
pages are the old version of the
internet uh that was on paper, right?
You may not know what that is. Uh
telephone companies would uh get people
to pay for advertising. They would drop
it off at your door. You could flip
through it. And it think the internet
except on actual yellow pages. That's
what he's referring to. Uh
I'm here to just help make connections
uh across generations. Um now Fred, to
be fair, right, you didn't say outright
negative. In fact, you you said and and
I'm going to pivot us because on
overture 5, you said I'd prefer to
answer that in reference to overture 26.
And and that may be a helpful way to
keep the conversation moving forward is
is to let you now kind of take up
overture 26 and say okay if at least
there's general agreement from what I
can tell let's not just do this right
now in this way there are other ways to
do this and for you Fred looking at
overure 26 that may be a better route to
take when you think what what are you
going to do with the diretory of worship
is that fair I think so yeah so I just
want to say first I'm glad that you
invited me to be the as the new
grandfather the young whippers snapper
on the panel I was in middle school in
1982. So, I'm glad to be the youth
movement here. Um, but you know, I think
there is a lot in the current section of
the directory of worship that almost
everyone would agree shouldn't be
constitutional. You know, you've heard
it seen in the in the internet that uh
the doxology should be sung at the
beginning of a service. I've never seen
that in my life. Um, most people don't
know what it means in the one
constitutional chapter to have the table
and the elements decently covered. And I
think it goes back to the time when
there wasn't air conditioning and they
tried to keep flies off the elements. So
there is work that needs to be done
here. But I think as David has pointed
out in a different arena, BCO25 actually
tells Sessions to order worship in
accordance with the directory. So rather
than have a long non-constitutional
conflicting directory, I would like to
see us in overture 26 approve a study
committee. I know we've got study
committee fatigue and they could take as
long as they want. They don't have to go
three chapters at a time, David. They
could present one chapter at a time. And
to try to make it consistent, I think it
should be much shorter. I think to How's
point, there should be almost all
shoulds and very little shales. We're
not creating a prayer book. The
directory for worship by definition
should not have forms. It should not
have a lot of binding matters. Um it
should just talk about what the emphasis
is for various things. And you know
looking at the current directory the
chapters that um are in this overture
not 26 but um the one that wants to make
60 to 63 constitutional.
I'm not even sure they need to be in a
directory. they might be better as an
appendix because they're not really
directly related to worship. I think
it's good to talk about, you know, um,
visiting the sick. It's good to think
about fasting, Christian life in the
home, etc. But what I would like us to
see is to get um for lack of a better
phrase, a blue ribbon panel from across
the PCA to find something, you know, a
way to slim this down and to give
guidance to sessions. I would think, for
example, there would be nothing in it
about types of instruments or number of
songs or length of prayers, anything
like that at all that would approach a
form. I would like to see it be a
quarter of the size that it is now, a
half of the size. That would just give
guidance to sessions because they're
already supposed to use this directory,
but it's not constitutional. That's what
I would like to see.
If I could uh
chime in here, um I liked Howie's point
that he he loved reformed worship before
he loved reformed theology. Uh I had an
experience not like that but um
uh years and years ago when I first read
Calvin on the necessity of reforming the
church I was absolutely shocked that the
almost the entire document is about
worship. I was expecting something on
justification by faith alone the
doctrine by which the church stands or
falls. And uh Calvin really
made his way toward doctrine through the
corruption of worship that needed to be
reformed. And that's quite a remarkable
thing. And I think that's one of the
deficiencies of not having a directory
for worship because
the um uh
we're committed that the scripture
governs worship and we ought to have
statements uh paraphrasing scripture
that shows us what things are necessary
and then uh maybe a short reference set
of references of things that might be
practically useful and then nothing
else.
Okay. Any other comments uh before we
move on to the next overure? Yeah, this
is Howie. Just real quick, if if we do
need to reform worship, I think it needs
to begin in the seminaries.
Uh I did a little research. If you can
get an MD from Greenville RTS and
Covenant Seminary
with two to three hours worship credit,
that's all. So I don't think we're
graduating guys that have read it nearly
as much about worship as I have. So part
of it is a seminary job more than a DO.
Although one of forefathers pointed out
that one of the virtues of a book of
church order is that it can be used as a
manual in the seminaries to train people
if it's well done.
Good point.
Can I just ask uh in terms of thinking
through uh the importance of this? Um
I've heard some case being made for uh
the founders of the PCA started to go
down this road uh with the directory of
worship. So there's kind of this, hey,
it's a construction project that's not
done. Uh let's pick that back up and
finish that construction project. Um
David, you just mentioned uh Calvin's
response to corruption of worship. My I
I'm going to venture guess that what
Calvin was contending with in terms of
variance in worship or what was
compatible incompatible in his day may
be slightly different than the
acrosstheboard view of the PCA churches.
And so can I just ask like is this more
of a historical let's finish a job or is
this more of a uh there's there's
corruption in worship practice in the
PCA right now that must be addressed and
the directory of worship is the best way
to address it just because that those
carry two different urgencies in my
mind. I just wonder what your each of
you what your take is on that. I I
um I have uh views that are considerably
more conservative than the PCA
generally, but also more conservative
than most of whoever the right wing of
the PCA is. For example, I don't think
choirs are warranted in churches in
worship services. I don't think solos
are warranted and I could go on but the
fact is I live with the fact that people
don't agree with me on that and I don't
think I'm sinning if I sit there and a
choir sings and I don't have any urgency
to try and persuade everybody that there
shouldn't be choir. So I don't s my
concern in the directory for worship is
not at all the reformation of the
current state of affairs in the PCA. My
concern is that we have a solid
scriptural foundation for our churches
and for worship leaders to be a guide
book.
Yeah, thank you so much Fred or Howie. I
would agree with that, Joel. I mean, I
don't think we're trying to or this
would even be a mechanism for trying to
root out corruption. You know, I'm I
think back to back when I was a ruling
elder 25 years ago. Uh in my presbyter,
there were significant efforts because
men were not fencing the table in
accordance with the constitutional
provisions of BCO you on the Lord's
supper. And so it being constitutional
didn't prevent problems. I don't think
it needs to prevent problems. I just
think it needs to do what what David's
saying, which is why I think it can be
much shorter than it is now. I also
think it's it's good to address the
anomaly that as far as I know, we may be
the only Presbyterian denomination that
doesn't have a constitutional directory.
And so, I'd like to see that resolved.
And I think if we had a shorter
constitutional directory, it might
actually take this out of the conflict
area because it would already be done
and we would say we're not going to say
more than this.
Yeah. Thank you, Fred. And earlier you
commented you thought there more shoulds
than shalls, which uh just for the
listener um what he's referencing there
is is it's common to read the BCO or the
book of church order in a way where a
shall is a mandate. this is exactly how
it it is to be done in your church and
to vary from that um is to be avoided
versus a should is a bit more in the
line of guidance. Um, uh, okay. Uh,
yeah, just very quick from a procedural
standpoint, I'm trying to figure out how
this plays out down the road. If there's
a study committee that prepares a
document, uh, if it's pres and it has
15 shalls or shall nots and it's
presented as a whole package, I don't
see how it passes twothirds of the
presbyter because different guys are
going to object to shall number one or
shall number two or shall number three.
Uh, but if you present it peace meal
like here, you get to vote on each of
the shells individually, that that gets
pretty awkward. So procedurally, I'm
just not sure how this thing even plays
out.
Well, there talking about the shall and
shoulds and thinking about worship. Uh
one of the last overtures in this
portion of the discussion that we wanted
to take up and thinking about worship is
that of overture number 12. Uh so
overture number 12 uh is a move to amend
BCO 585 and it focuses on uh the
distribution
uh of the Lord's supper. And just as a
quick note um my understanding from
reading your various guides, everyone
agrees that teaching elders according to
the book of church order in this
constitutional chapter, they're the ones
who administer the Lord's supper. So
everyone agrees to that. That's the
practice constitutionally for every PCA
church. A teaching elder uh is the one
who administers the supper. In uh
overture number 12 from Providence
Presbyter, uh the move would be to bring
a bit more direction. Um while the word
shall isn't used exactly in the
language, it seems like the manner it
this is the manner in which the elements
are to be distributed and then it
references the officers. And so, uh, in
reading your guides, as as I understood
it, maybe Fred, you were the most open
to this. Uh, seemed like Howie and David
were, uh, responded in the negative to
this. You kind of recognized some of
this and said, "Hey, there needs to be
some amendment." So, you weren't
necessarily framing over 12 in its
current construction. I just wanted to
give you a chance to speak to the value
that you thought was there. Yeah. So I
think there is a lack of clarity by the
term distribution. I don't think the
overture was intended and if it was
intended I wouldn't agree with it to bar
passing the plate in the pews right from
person to person. I think what we're
talking about here is the teaching elder
administering giving the words of
institution and then the elders
overseeing the sacrament. And from a
ruling elder perspective, which both of
my colleagues here are or have been
ruling elders, one of the jobs during
communion is not just to see how quick
the plates can be passed, but to see
who's taking and who's not because, for
example, someone may be in good standing
and not take the elements. That's a
pastoral conversation that needs to
happen. And so I think it should be done
by those who have shephering
administration of the flock. I'm not
exactly sure how we can get there from
here. I'm already starting to try to
think about amendments. I don't think as
a regular matter lay people uh should be
overseeing in a sense the distribution
of the elements. Uh I think it should be
officers who have been voted in there uh
who have a spiritual responsibility for
the flock. But again I I notice that
there is this difficulty here. I'm not
sure exactly without inventing a new
verb how that can be done. So I have
some consternation about that. Sure.
Thanks uh Fred. Um Howie David any
thoughts, reflections, any comments you
want to make? Yeah, if we have time. Um,
couple things.
Um, when I took ecclesiology and
sacraments from Sinclair Ferguson RTS
Orlando 5-day class, he said he didn't
see a reason why ruling elders
themselves couldn't administer the
sacraments. That's not a position I
hold, but uh I was kind of surprised by
that. Um, I think it kind of depends on
in our church, we have trays that people
hold up front. Um, if the person is just
holding the tray and not saying
anything, I'm not sure why that's an
officer requirement. The point Fred
brings up is valid, but
I can observe who takes and who doesn't
take better by standing in the back than
by holding the bread or the the cups up
front because I'm looking at the people
that come up front when when that
happens. So, um,
and lastly, the the more I've studied 1
Corinthians 11, the more I'm convinced
this is a family meal.
And
in our family, it's more than just me
that passes out the food or things like
that. So, I think there's a an
important, frankly, theological
component to having more than just
officers, old trays up front. So
um
I
I can't see in the scripture anywhere
that uh there's anything that leads me
to the conclusion that only officers can
touch the trays to get the implements to
the people in the church. I can't see
anything like that. And uh I mean I but
in my judgment we are all the time
adding to what the scripture says in the
communion service. I can't tell you how
many churches I've been in said well
because uh you must covenant with God
separately. You uh eat the bread when it
comes. And because uh we are a unity in
a family, we must all uh uh drink the
cup together. Now, those things are
true, but there's nothing in the
scripture says that that that's part of
the ceremony of the Lord's supper. I
think that is an illicit addition to the
ceremony. It ought to be as simple as
price institution.
And who passes what, when, and where, I
can't see any.
I I don't even since we want to have
some disagreement now, I'll disagree
slightly with Fred. I don't think uh
it's anybody's business who takes and
who doesn't take. If someone comes to
the pastor and says I I can't take
communion, that's but it being kind of
observed and then uh sought out. I don't
see any warrant for that myself.
I'd like to agree slightly with Fred's
position on a different part of this and
that is I don't think it's helpful if
for example there's a
20-year-old single gal holding the tray
with the cups and when you come forward
she says take this is Christ's blood
shed for you because that's that's kind
of a official proclamation kind of
thing. So to me the difference between
that and her just holding it are are
significant. So yeah absolutely
absolutely. Yeah. I just uh uh clean up
a few things. I understood Fred to be
suggesting the importance of the
shephering office overseeing it as
relating to potentially church
discipline there. So if for instance
there was someone coming who was under
discipline that wouldn't be widely known
and yet there seems to be some weight or
responsibility on the officers of that
but let's say the session of the church
uh to to enforce or to exercise
oversight over that discipline. So
that's what I understood him to be
referring to Fred would it is it more
expansive than that or am I off on my
understanding? I I guess all I would say
again to differ slightly with David is I
have actual experience with this. Uh
when I was a ruling elder, we were
serving the Lord's supper and there was
a longtime member in good standing who
didn't take the supper. And I went up to
him and just asked if everything was
okay.
And that was the straw that broke the
camel's back that he blurted out that he
had been committing adultery and wanted
to repent. And I mean, it opened up a
floodgate. It was just a simple
question. I didn't, you know, put him
under a flashlight and whatever. I just
think there are pastoral moments like
that and someone could just say, "Well,
I just had a tough day." And I wouldn't
grill them, but I think there is a
pastoral moment. And you know, that's
one of those opportunities. Uh it's
probably in some sense not that
different if someone in the congregation
appeared to be by body language and face
completely not paying attention or
hostile to the sermon. I think you would
do the same thing. Sure. Well, hopefully
there isn't a ruling a young ruling
elder listening to this who's thinking,
"Well, if I'm holding the trays up there
and some person comes up who's not
authorized to take the supper, I'm going
to cause a fuss up front and try to keep
them away." That would be probably an
unwise thing to do. Follow up later, but
on the spot, I can envision that to be
an ugly situation. Joint and several
responsibilities. You don't you don't
have individual responsibility. Yeah,
that's right. Well, and furthermore,
that that would be an exercise of force
in discipline which we have nothing to
do with. It's purely a voluntary matter.
And if a person comes and eats there, we
shouldn't tackle them. Now, you could
finally put them out for trespassing if
they disrupt the service, but there's no
force in relationship to the
administration of our discipline. Yeah.
Because you would be, as I understand
you, David, you're saying biblically,
say from 1 Corinthians 11, while it's a
family meal, it's ultimately going to be
the Lord who judges and then exercises
that judgment if if someone eats in an
unworthy way. Right. Right.
Well, uh I I think that brings us to the
end of our first uh discussion time and
uh covering uh overtures um uh five,
overture 26, and overture 12. Thanks so
much, uh for each of you weighing in and
and being willing to uh discuss and work
through. We hope it's uh to a benefit
for those who are listening or watching.